<Document>
# Genetics

Genetics on Trauma Station is based off of /tg/station with some slight differences in gameplay.

All mutations from tg are implemented here!

# Disks

<Box>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="GeneticsDisk"/>
</Box>

Rather than the genetics console having infinite storage, you have to store each mutation on a genetics disk. A hand labeler will save your life here.

Your locker will have a box of disks but you can print more in the sci techfab.

# Sequencing

To sequence a mutation, unlocking it and activating it in the subject, solve the gene puzzle so that every A is paired with a T, every C with a G.

For single missing bases this is trivial, but with missing pairs you will need to do some thinking. Or just brute force it and torture your poor monkeys.

Any incorrect guess when sequencing will severely damage the subject's genome. Get some medicine from chem or more monkey cubes to prepare for this.

# Solving missing base pairs

<Box>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="HandheldGeneticsScanner"/>
</Box>

There is no joker button. Go outside of your lab and scan people, or Pun Pun, with your [bold]handheld genome scanner[/bold]. You can use logic to deduce what missing bases in your subjects are by finding multiple people with the same dormant mutation.

Every mutation in the game has a random number assigned each round, however they stay the same between different subjects with the same mutation.

For example, if you have a monkey in the lab with a genome with an unknown first pair, then scan someone with that mutation and a known first pair, you can use that pair to finish the sequence.

# Biomass

Biomass is needed to print mutators, activators and cleansers. Source it from botany, loose corpses, etc. then put it in your console.
Think carefully if you need to give every lowly assistant hulk, you won't have any biomass left to print anything else!

# Removing Mutations

To remove mutations instead of using mutadone, you print a cleanser from the storage tab using a disk with the mutation you want to remove. Inject it and the mutation is gone!

# Scrambling DNA

If monkeys are in extra short supply and you are having bad luck, you can use the [bold]Scramble DNA[/bold] button to reroll any dormant mutations the subject has.
It will receive a lot of damage though, so get some meds.

# Combining

Combining mutations is done with a "catalyst" mutation stored on the current disk, and any mutation the subject already has.

If you pick a correct combination the result is added, but it is not sequenced! You will need to combine it with many subjects for the complex mutations in order to get enough bases.

# Research

One of the biggest differences from tg is that [bold]you actually contribute to research![/bold]. You get 8000 points for sequencing most mutations, with more complex ones having higher rewards.

# Unique Enzymes

Disks can also store a person's [bold]unique enzymes[/bold] which can be used to copy their name, sex, fingerprints and eye/skin color to another subject.

This won't copy their DNA or current hair styles. Get a pair of scissors and set up a barbershop!

</Document>
